howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is ron abramitsky
professor of economics at stanford and
the newly appointed
senior associate dean of social sciences
in the school of humanities and sciences
his professional interests are focused
on economic history and applied
economics with focus
on immigration and income equality
gee thanks for having me i'm happy to be
here ah great to have you here
today we'll be talking about ron's book
the mystery of the kibbutz egalitarian
principles in a capitalist
world this is an area i've been
researching for a while
possible application in contemporary
community building
and society tuning you know how can we
get to a more egalitarian way of life
and i read another book on the kibbutz
movement that for people who want an
absurd amount of history probably more
than you'd ever want to know
called the kibbutz movement the history
origins and growth by henry near
two thick volumes though i would say for
most people
ron's book will will give you plenty and
also will address some very
interesting intersections between the
ideology of egalitarianism
and what we know from western style
economics and we'll get to that in a
moment but before we hop into that
i'd love ron to talk a little bit about
how his family and his family's history
intersects the kibbutz movement
yeah so thanks again jim for having me
my interest in the kibbutz really came
from the
contradictions between my wonderful
experiences of the kibbutz growing up
and then my more skeptical self when i
grew up a little more i did not grow up
myself
in the kibbutz but my entire life was
around the kibbutzi my grandmother
was the proud founder of wonky boots in
the south and my
and she lived there for 55 years my
mother grew up there and left
my uncle and aunt still lived there my
brother lived there
so we would visit as children my brother
and i with the family my grandmother
every week and it was wonderful we love
the kibbutz you know a society that is
based on full
equal sharing at the time in the 70s it
was this picturesque
village with green paths and swimming
pools and the dining hall
and we would play basketball and table
tennis we would wander around the
kibbutz our parents didn't have to worry
about us
because it was so safe it was just
wonderful and then when i
grew a little older when i became a
teenager i love the kibbutz even more
because the idea
of sharing everything equally seemed
like the
justice the the right thing the fair
thing
to do but then as i grew a bit more
and especially after i started to study
economics at the
hebrew university i became a little bit
like the other side of the cliche
you know that if you are younger than 20
and you are not a socialist it means you
have no heart but if you are over 20 and
you are still a socialist
it means you have no brain and so i
remember
one day in the late 90s when i we were
visiting my
uncle and aunt in the kibbutz in the
north
and we would sit down and my uncle would
describe one of his
path-breaking innovations of the
irrigation factory of his kibbutz and i
decided to
provoke him and i said you know
according to economic theory
your factory shouldn't be as good in
fact the entire enterprise of the
kibbutz should not really exist
and he's like what what are you talking
about and i said well
you know why would anybody work hard
if all you get anyway is an equal share
of the total output so i explained to
him the
free rider problem that we studied in
economics and then i
said i expect that everybody would be
lazy in the kibbutz
and then why would anybody that can earn
more outside the kibbutz and is so
talented and brilliant why would
he ever stay israel is the size of new
jersey
you can always live and earn more like
in tel aviv why would
i so i expect i explained to him the
brain drain problem
whereby i expect all the brilliant
people to move away from the keyboards
and then
i said well what about entry i expect
that
everybody that can't make it outside the
kibbutz
all the lazy people would want to enter
a kibbutz what a great deal it is to be
subsidized by all the brilliant
more educated people in the kibbutz and
i
continued with my super annoying speech
of mine and i said well i also worry a
bit about the children in the kibbutz
because
why would anybody study hard when
we're like a high school dropout and a
computer science engineer earned just as
much
and so he you know then he got upset of
course
and he we started a nice fight and he
said oh you economists are so cynical
and you know anybody familiar with the
kibbutz knows that
founders of kibbutzim were anything but
these selfish people
and if you're so smart then you know how
could you explain that the kibbutz
survived
for so long despite all these problems
you are describing and it got me
thinking and to begin with i wasn't as
cynical as i made myself sound and
that's it ever since then i studied
decided to study
how conch would seem survive for so long
despite all their economic
contradictions and then
more broadly how when whether we can
create a more equal
society and under what conditions it can
succeed
exactly yeah when i read that i go yeah
i definitely want to track this guy down
and have him on the show
because it's a wonderful contradiction
right because you know based on the same
kinds of economics i learned when i was
in college
you'd say nope kabut's impossible and
yet here they are a hundred years later
right
so there has to be something else that
was missing from the analysis
that would be real helpful for our
guests who who no doubt
know vaguely what a kibbutz is is if you
could do as you do in the book in the
first chapter or so
and go into a little bit of the history
you know just a relative short arc
of the history of the kibbutz movement
and you know basically take it up to say
you know it's not go to the crisis but
up to about then
sure let me do it briefly let me know if
you want more details so so kibbutzim
plural of kibbutz are communities in
israel
that were based for many years on full
income equality in the distribution of
incomes
and on collective ownership of all
properties that
were indeed always a small percentage of
the population of israel the first
kibbutz
ghania was established southwest of the
sea of galilee
in 1910 by a dozen russian and eastern
european jewish immigrants but really
the majority
of kibbutzim were established in the 30s
and 40s just before the state of israel
was established today there are about a
hundred and twenty thousand members
living in 268 kibbutzim and they account
for about
two percentage of the jewish population
in israel
at most kibbutz members accounted for up
to seven percent of the population
around the time
the state of israel was created but
nevertheless they met
a great deal despite the low percentage
they mattered a great deal
in the context of israel and more
broadly as social experiments that teach
us about
whether and how we can create more equal
society so the kibbutz was
it's more broadly than just equal
sharing it was a way of life if you want
a social unit
that was created to fulfill a wide array
of ideas you know building the jewish
nation
creating a socially just society and
being part of a community that promotes
equality
and mutual assistance they they took
communal living so seriously that they
had these dining halls where people
would not eat in their comfort of their
own homes
but they would eat together in communal
dining halls
they took equality so seriously that at
some point they created these separate
communal residences for
children whereby children would not live
in their parents homes but rather would
live in separate new residences with a
nanny and they would visit maybe their
parents a couple of hours a day maybe
from four to six
it was the no cash economy for many
years and so no savings and
they took equality so seriously that
even they distributed goods in kind
rather than
with money so you had you would have a
budget for traveling for clothing
for food and so on and while always home
to small
percentage of the jewish population they
had a huge impact on the rest of israeli
society
in the 30s and 40 they started at
communal farms
but in the 50s and 60s when israel went
through industrialization process
hebrew team participated in this process
and since then they have
a large industrial base alongside
agriculture in the 70s and 80s when my
brother and i would visit them
the quality of life there was quite high
it's not that there weren't crisis over
the years there was an ideological
crisis
in the 50s around the support in the
cold war in russia
versus the united states there was a
discussion about like whether members
should be allowed to work outside or not
there was a discussion a crisis about
whether we should allow
they should allow uh private allowances
uh
that kibbutz members can buy stuff but
despite all these crisis the quality of
life in kibbutzim
in the seventh and in the 70s was higher
than
many other citizens of israel and that's
despite
the full equality and now communal
ownership
of property so i'm happy to go into more
details yeah
i'll also make the point i just looked
up unfortunately data isn't totally
current but on wikipedia
this morning it said that the kibbutz is
as of 2010 while only two percent of the
population
are nine percent of israel's industrial
output worth about
eight billion dollars and forty percent
of the agricultural output worth 1.7
billion so
while a small percent of the population
economically they punch way above their
weight particularly in the
kind of the fundamental production of
goods right and
indeed as i recall the ideology of the
original founders of the kibbutz
was to encourage the jewish people to
return to fundamental production rather
than living in
you know more professional more abstract
types of
occupations exactly so they said exactly
so they were at first
exactly like you say they they were
meant to uh
they they thought that the only way for
the jewish people to survive is to
return to the land
and work in the kind of productive
quote-unquote occupations like
in agriculture and so on rather than
study the torah and
working in more professional occupations
but then again they
started to all build factories in the
60s and 70s and as you mentioned
despite the small percentage of the
population they are higher percentage of
industrial production in israel so they
had high economic social
military status kibbutz members and they
had a disproportionate impact on the
ideological political and military
leadership of israel they produce some
of israel's elite like from famous
generals like
igal alon and barak to famous musicians
like shalom khan
the academia is full of former kibbutz
members
yeah we'll return to that later in that
you know the kibbutz is
interesting and and somewhat unlike a
lot of other communal
attempts elsewhere in the world and that
at least after the early days the
kibbutz nicks were not marginal i mean
these were
in some sense the elite of israeli as
you point out they
disproportionately into military
leadership and the arts
and all kinds of interesting things and
that's worth the audience keeping in
mind these were not a bunch of
rejectionist hippies right these were
people playing the game seriously but
just in a different way
exactly this is you know this is what
got me so interested in them because
unlike a lot of other communists in
history as you said they were never in
the margin of society they always
influenced and were influenced by
society around them they will
they would go to schools uh high schools
with the
non-ki boots members they would serve in
the military with non kibbutz members
uh and so at some level it's more
interesting it's not like
the amish or like or like other communes
that
maybe they have such different belief
system than society around them
that it just makes sense for them to
group by themselves in in a somewhat
isolated place
kibbutz members at some level they are
so interesting to me for me to study
because
despite being so central they choose to
live
in that way even though many of them can
live elsewhere
and even though they do see society
around them and how other people
live yeah that and that makes them to my
mind more
interesting actually as a model exactly
and that
you know it shows that it may well be
possible to build egalitarian
bubbles inside even a capitalist society
and make them sustainable the boots did
it
quite successfully for quite a while and
some of them are still working doing it
successfully to this day
another little bit about the history
which i found utterly fascinating
which is that the puts was not a
monolithic movement there were different
flavors of kibbutz you know there was
kibbutz artsy which was more
ideologically pure and then there was
kibbutz muhad is that it how you
pronounce it
became the united kibbutz movement which
was more pragmatic i suppose in
political
and then there was a cavazot association
that argued for no more than 200 members
per kibbutz while the
muhad said make them as big as possible
right so they were
from my jewish friends they say hey you
know if you get two jews together
there'll be three opinions
at least right seems to have been true
about
essentially the style of kibbutz and
some of these things merged and they'd
split again and then there was always a
small orthodox jewish religious oriented
kibbutz movement that really didn't have
much to do with the other kibbutz
so maybe talk just a little bit about
those organizations and styles of
kibbutz
yeah absolutely i would first say though
to your previous point that another
thing that is interesting about their
model is that beyond
let's say the other communes in history
it's also they didn't choose the model
of the
soviet union for example or other
socialist countries
that are totalitarian and would you know
in a russian cohort for example if you
exit they
they would kill you well that's not a
very interesting economic decisions then
of whether to stay or live rather than
the more voluntary model that they took
as for the movements the movements are
all have a fascinating history that i
discussed in some detail in my book
interestingly they were never very
important in the day-to-day life of
kibbutzim
they didn't have any say on how each
individual keyboard exactly
handled their business as well they did
some but not a lot but
mostly they coordinated their actions
and would seem affiliated themselves
with movements of different ideological
bands so as you mentioned
some of them are more ideological than
others that's the kibbutz rt
others are more that's the kibbutz mohad
as you said
and and for many years in the eyes of
the outside world
out even outside israel never people
never understood really
what it means you know like whether you
belong to that movement or this movement
but then it it was interesting
especially in the 50s
around the cold war when there was a
really fierce debate
among kibbutz members of whether they
should support
the us or the soviet union you know like
in the
cold war and kibbutzim actually split
over these
ideological decisions you know like and
some and then they became ahad versus
you know really in fact there are
stories of families even splitting into
two over this debate and
this was kind of like people outside of
the kibbutz israelis were scratching
their heads saying
what are they talking about why is that
so important for the way they live but
then uh
later in the book i do find that he
would seem that we're associated with
the more ideological movements
were less likely to undertake reforms
and they were slower to adapt the
changes
that we might that we are going to shift
away from equal sharing that we may be
talking about a bit later in the talk
okay and again it makes fascinating
reading and the ebb and flow and the
relationship but the politics
yeah it's fascinating we won't go into
it today but i would say people are
interested in that's included in the
book and then the
henry near book goes into it in
exhausting detail
which i found interesting but as you
said in your speech to your uncle there
are
seemingly some contradictions from an
economic perspective
about the kibbutz free rider problem
adverse selection brain drain
and we'll get to those later but before
we do you had a nice section in your
book where you kind of stood on its head
and said why might an economist create a
kibbutz
yeah so what are the economic advantages
at least in theory
and as it turned out i think in practice
at least in part of something like a
kibbutz
so imagine the founders of kibbutzim who
decide to
get the advice of an economist about
whether and how they should
create their keyboards well you know if
the economist was a very
narrow-minded cynical as i presented
myself to my uncle he would say that's a
terrible idea
it would collapse very quickly don't do
that
but if this economist had the foresight
of how economics would develop
over the next century or so and if he
was humble enough to borrow
insights from some of the other social
sciences from history
then it's very likely that he would tell
them to create the kibbutz
pretty much the way they ended up
creating it well
not exactly he would for sure have give
more voice to women
avoid some of the corruption that took
place in the higher ups of kibbutzim
sometimes
but pretty much the way they they
created it and so maybe he would say at
first
he would say well you know like now that
i get over my
uh instincts that equality might create
incentive problems
beyond all the other reasons that you
mentioned to me like the socialist
ideology altruism fairness
considerations maybe philosophical
ideals
like the rosian ideals of equality i can
actually see
an economic advantage of creating
kibbutz in a purely economic advantage
and that is that a kibbutz gives you a
terrific
insurance a safety net against all the
problems and miseries that life can
bring you so in a kibbutz you know that
regardless of what happens to you
whether you become disabled whether you
your profession is becoming out of style
whether you get injured whether you have
children
that face some problems regardless of
your circumstances you and your family
would always be
getting paid the same and this is a
terrific insurance that no other place
can offer you and so though he would of
course say
you should still worry about all these
incentive programs because the insurance
arrangement can
collapse if you don't worry about it and
then he would say well i have some
advice for you
you would say first of all i really
strongly suggest for you to bring highly
idealistic people
to your effort so don't just bring these
cynical people that are so selfish that
they only care about themselves
but rather try to bring people that
share the same ideological and
vocational training
that are idealistic that they have
shared in common goals
you know my those kind of people
idealistic people they don't share you
know my grandmother
did not miss a day of work in 55 years
she lived in a kibbutz idealistic people
they contribute anyway even when there
are no incentives
and then he will tell them to they'll
build the kibbutz in such a way that
would
avoid all this incentive you know he
would tell them don't trust though
on the idealistic nature of people
because the second generation like often
happens
for the children of the founders living
in the kibbutz is no longer a choice
it's a default you know you grew up into
this and when this happens
practical considerations often become
more important than idealistic
considerations
and so you should build your society in
such a way that will help you avoid
all these incentive problems we in a way
that pretty much like didn't i can go in
details to that but i will let you
do you want me to continue to talk or do
you want to ask a question
yeah once you continue to drill into it
a little bit i'll just point out too
that you mentioned
one is that in you can go into the
examples there's opportunities for
increasing return to scale
in some activities right classic
microeconomics
and then also there's certainly some
opportunities for public goods
if you design your boots correctly maybe
talk about those and other
economic forces that work to hold the
kibbutz together
great so imagine the so the economist
would say okay how should you build the
kibbutz
well what about let's think about free
the free riding problem you know the
tendency of people to not pull in the
way
with the weight when there is full equal
sharing well how about social sanctions
you know in kibbutz everybody knows
everybody you work in the same place you
live in
your kids go to the same schools
kibutsim are all
you know the size between about 100
people to a thousand people the average
size of a kibbutz is around
440 members which is about 150 or 200
families
so they can make in the kibbutz they can
make your life sufficiently miserable
that you are better off living rather
than not working hard
you don't work hard they wouldn't sit
next to you in the dining hall they
would let you feel
awful but of course the thing is that
for social sanctions to be effective
you kind of need to design a relatively
small community
because social sanctions don't uh you
know work in a
huge country of like when not everybody
knows everybody and this is despite as
you say
there are many reasons for why creating
one
large kibbutz has benefits over creating
many small ones there are what
economists call
returns to scale you know some services
like
laundry and food are cheaper to
produce in large quantities relative
than in small quantities
and in fact there was a debate in the
kibbutz at some point about whether they
should
as you mentioned earlier whether they
should allow only 200 people
or whether they should make it larger
and it always gets to well let's keep
them we still have to keep them small
enough
in order for everybody to know everybody
and you know for social sanctions to be
effective that's
that's essential you don't find jaw you
don't find a job
no problem you know the kibbutz work
organizer will send you to peel potatoes
in the chicken so there is no such thing
as unemployment in the kibbutz everybody
is working
and of course the other side of social
sanctions is
a social reward if you want so like
rotations in leadership so unlike many
other communes
it was never in the key but it was never
one charismatic leader that is the
leader of the kibbutz for 50 years
leadership is rotated so the kibbutz
manager the farm manager
the kibbutz secretary those are jobs
that are rotated and that they are
always given to people who are perceived
to be doing
more than their share now adverse
selection you worry about people that
are the
that are lazy or didn't make it outside
you want them you worry that they might
enter the keyboards
believe me the kibbutzim are well aware
of this problem
and in fact if you want to enter they
have tough screening processes
for people who want to join you have to
show that you're able to
make a living in the kibbutz that you
have a high enough education
there is even once you get in even once
they let you in you are on a probation
period for a year or two
until they vote they get to know you and
they vote
whether to allow you to stay of course
in the
founding generation this was an easier
problem because
the founders were all young people who
share
similar ideology and training and they
had like if you want similar prospects
and so it's the homogeneity of people
that were very similar that naturally
solve
the other selection problem but it's
less likely that a
computer science engineer would want to
create a keyboard with a
high school dropout and this is why they
go through the screening now the tougher
problem is
is the is the brain drain what about
brain how do you make sure
that people who are in the kibbutz
members of the kibbutz maybe they they
joined when they were young but at some
point people realize if they are
very bright and all they they have an
ability to earn much more in tel aviv
how do you make sure they stay
well the economist would tell them why
don't you abolish all private property
have all property owned collectively and
if you
want to leave no problem you can take
your brain with you but you cannot take
your share of the kibbutz
you cannot take your part of the factory
you cannot take your house
you cannot take the swimming pool and
the dining hall and so
that makes exit costly there is no money
for many years and so there is no
ability to save and so there is no
bequest
so makes it makes it difficult to live
even if you are very ambitious you want
to study no problem the kibbutz would
allow you to study agronomy
but not law so they would let you study
stuff that is more valuable in the
kibbutz and all these things
make it uh make exit costing now i wanna
i
just wanna say that of course i'm not
saying that all these
norms and rules in the kibbutz were
decided just in order to
solve the incentive problems there are
many ideological and other reasons for
communal ownership of property and uk
and communal education for children and
dining hall
the point is that whether they meant it
or not whether they designed it on
purpose or not
they created a society that was very
helpful for them
to maintain equality for a long period
of time
yeah today it seems like they probably
didn't study economics to come up with
these and as you said these
innovations were probably emerged for a
whole bunch of reasons
but interestingly they they tended to
address these fundamental economic
problems that you
suggest you know the milton friedman
story of the billiard player right that
even though the billiard player doesn't
know
physics doesn't have to know physics in
order to be an excellent player
it doesn't mean that the rules of
physics don't apply on the table you
still have to hit the ball
in a certain angle taking it into
account the friction in order for the
ball to land in the
in the hole so it is like they acted as
if
they uh know all the uh you know they
know the you know the you know economics
if you want and
created the society to deal with that in
a way that
was helpful to deal with incentive
problems makes perfect sense to me
though of course there are trade-offs
around quality of life for instance
you point out and others do as well that
one of the most important ways to
manage the free rider problem with
social sanctions is privacy
has to be pretty limited and in the
early days
you know that one of the the core
phenomena at the
kibbutz was the dining hall right life
in many ways seemed to be central around
the dining hall that's where
arts events happened etc but then over
time
you know so some kibbutz has allowed
families to have their own kitchens etc
and so presumably sort of radical
transparency started going down a little
bit and i suspect free rider problems
could have gone up
any thoughts on that yeah exactly so so
you ask yourself if it's so amazing and
they provide you such a terrific
insurance
and the equality is is a value that many
of us like and
we want to live that way how come
kibutim always exists in israel although
if you are me you see
elements of kibbutzim everywhere we can
talk about it later but but
how come they are such a small
percentage even of the population of
israel you know two percentage of the
population
at most they were seven and one of them
is that uh
in order for you to in order for this to
work you need social sanctions for
example
uh you need it means lack of privacy
everybody in the kibbutz knows you're
coming and going
you need to have communal ownership of
property that is something that many
people don't like
until this day you ask my mom hey mom
where are you going she says
you know what i stopped answering that
question 45 years ago when i left the
kibbutz don't ask me
what i'm up to where i'm going i want to
i want to live my life without people
knowing my coming and going
and so if you want that lack of privacy
and
the lack of private property which was
so essential in the traditional kibbutz
to
help solve some of the incentive
problems are stuff that many people
don't
don't like and maybe that explains why
it is so
if you want the kibbutz is almost like
an experiment to know how many people
would like to live that way so you can
ask yourself the question
if people were given a choice of whether
to live in a society
where all incomes and resources are
shared equally
how many people would choose to do it
and if you want
the kibbutz gives you some answer you
know like up to seven percent
of the population interesting and though
of course you also have to adjust that
by how many are rejected by the adverse
selection screening
it might be higher but if you make the
intersection of those who would like to
and are capable of exactly that's right
so it could be it could be larger if
it would be that the perfect experiment
would be to allow free entry to the
kibbutz
uh or and to see like how many people uh
would join and i think a few kabuts
tried that in the early days and found
it was a disaster right
not so much in the early days as much as
in the in the 19 in the early 1980s
there are stories of some kibutim
trying to open their doors to uh you
know to open the doors and were not very
happy with their decision at some level
though if you want that's a that's
another
that's another price if you want of
creating an equal sharing society is
that the kibbutzim were never very
inclusive
so with if you want the price of
equality
inside the kibbutz means also inequality
across groups because you you know if
you you have to show that you can
earn a living in the kibbutz they
wouldn't let you in if you don't have
enough education
if you you know they didn't accept arabs
you know if the kibbutz is a jewish
phenomena
even you know it's mostly ashkenazi
jewish phenomena even though today they
would
accept you even if you're not of course
but if you want
the screening the kibbutz point to the
price of equal sharing which is that it
is not very inclusive
in its equality yeah and i did extract
that actually while i was
reading is that again it seems like the
billiard player they probably maybe not
had thought about this explicitly but
a certain amount of coherence and
similarity of people and the ability to
read
people so that you can understand them
helps maintain
this kind of system and i suspect that
that may have been part of the
driving force why it's almost purely
ashkenazi at least for a long time and
relatively few sephardim the homogeneity
is
at some level if you think about it more
broadly it is not
homogeneity makes it easier to maintain
equality
and it is not surprising that there is
more equality
in countries like sweden and norway
where the population is more homogeneous
than
than in the united states where the
population is more
heterogeneous and it is more difficult
to uh define
common goals if you want yeah yeah i
think that's an important point you know
unfortunately i think it's just the
reality that diversity is a value but
it's not a
monotonically increasing value right i
give the example suppose you lived in a
community of 150 families and every
single one of them
was from a different culture and spoke a
different language and none of them knew
two languages
that would not be a very pleasant place
to live right so you know
there's an optimal amount of diversity
like there's an optimal amount of
everything and
i suspect that in a mission like a
kibbutz the amount
of diversity that is tolerable to keep
the high enough level of coherence is
probably smaller than an open market
driven society yeah the diversity
does make it more difficult for them to
create this is also but although this is
one reason why for example if you think
about national insurance programs they
typically are mandatory so social
insurance is mandatory exactly
because you worry that only the
healthiest wealthiest people would
join it and so for sure it is a
diversity makes it more
difficult to sustain equality but it
also brings the broader question about
how much
really we should consider it equality
if it is only equality among such a
small
and homogeneous group of people so how
fair it is to call it
that you live with that you know if you
want to do equality because you believe
in fairness
and you believe that everybody is equal
and you believe that everybody should
have equal opportunity
then how serious we should take you if
you're only doing it among a small group
of homogeneous people
yeah that's certainly a real issue for
people that are trying to say think
about
launching such communities today now
there's another economic
conundrum that you pointed out a little
bit more subtle perhaps
than the other ones which are relatively
straightforward
and that is the problem of human capital
investment
here's the words you use why should
kovitz members study hard if a high
school dropout working in the kibbutz
kitchen and a computer scientist
running the most profitable business in
the combusts enjoyed the same living
standards
maybe talk about that a little bit and
how the economics economic forces at
least
would have a tendency to impact human
capital investment
yes so this is a very interesting
question and
as you say it's a bit more subtle my
first intuition
for my skepticism came again from this
conversation with my uncle where i said
you know
why would you study hard in school why
would you stress over exams why would
you choose fields of study
that are difficult if you have no
returns to your education if you want
there are zero returns to education in
egalitarian kibbutz the financial
returns to education are zero
because if your high school dropout or
if you are a computer science engineer
you get paid exactly the same now
that's from the individual perspective
from the kibbutz perspective
they in addition to that they have
conflicting incentives because on the
other on the one hand if you want as
extended family they would like to have
their children study whatever it is that
they want but on the other hand as an
employer
they might work they also want their
employers to be educated that's another
reason to want high level of human
capital
but on the other hand they might worry
that if you are really very educated
you might want to leave and if all the
bright all the very educated people
leave
this is a problem for the kibbutz so
one of the things and so this is kind of
if you want the theory now
i looked at the numbers i looked at the
data and you know a lot of what i'm
doing relies on the large data sets that
i collected
for the 100 years of kibbutz existence
and one of the things i do in terms of
human capital is i ask the simple
question well
well then are kibbutz members less
educated than the general population
so in order to make a fair comparison i
say okay kibusi means a jewish phenomena
they mostly have ashkenazi jews well
archibus members
much less educated than the ashkenazi
jewish population
outside of kibutim if there are such
lack of incentives to study
and the answer is not really so the
average the average kibbutz member even
in the periods of the
of equal sharing on average they are
similarly educated to the ashkenazi
population outside
of course they you know in the margin
there are differences so for example
less of them
are completely uneducated relative to
the general population but also fewer of
them have maybe very advanced
degrees but this is one thing that i
take as if you want
suggestive against this a simple
economic theory of
studying because of the financial
returns heboots members were always
educated even when there were no
financial returns to it and this is
suggesting that of course
but many people know that you don't just
study for the financial returns there
are other reasons
why you want to study now economic
theory is not
completely wrong here so for example we
do find in a work that i'm doing with
my collaborator victor lavie from the
hebrew university and then later also
with my young
segev we look at what happens when
once the keyboard seems shift away from
equal sharing maybe we can talk about
that and we do find that
kibbutz students do start to take school
more seriously once their keyboards
shift away from equal sharing and they
do start to take
fields that are more potentially
profitable so
they do respond to incentives it's not
like the incentive problems stop at the
gate of the kibbutz
but but but maybe the maybe economic
incentives to study are not the main
reason of why people study hard and what
fields they choose
and as always it's a mix i mean the idea
to declare humans to be homo economic is
almost always fails right
by the other hand homo economicus is a
part of who we are
i would hypothesize i wonder if you have
the answer to this is that in the
full equal earnings period was there a
bias away from the liberal arts say
history and literature versus
say engineering or nursing yes exactly
so that's what we tend to find there is
a bias
there is actually once the key boots
shift away from equal sharing
later with a period we didn't talk about
yet but once the keyboards shift away
from equal sharing later
you start to see that young adults in
the kibbutz become more likely
to study fields like engineering and
sciences in general as opposed to
a liberal arts in the equal sharing
period they were more likely to study
history and arts and and humanities
that have a global economic financial
returns outside of the keyboards
very interesting yeah we'll get to soon
the crisis and then transition
but before that i want to talk about
just a couple of interesting issues that
came out that don't really fit into
either the pre or post bucket
i guess they've actually occurred in the
pre period one
is the ideology versus the reality of
gender equality
yeah so the kibbutz it's exactly the way
you say there is a very
big gap between the ideology and the
reality
of gender equality in the kingdoms as
people who consider themselves taking
equality
very seriously many kibbutzim also
was striving for gender equality and
that meant that
women were fighting in the wars they
were
they were they were supposed to working
in all those occupations
that men work in and most importantly
one of the arguments for creating a real
gender equality is to free up
women from their traditional role in
society of raising kids
and that gave rise one of the reasons
that gave rise to the
separate residences for children where
children all grow up in outside of their
parents homes
and the parents get to see them a couple
of hours but then every
couple in the kibbutz have a gets a
small
apartment just for the couple and that
should free women from the traditional
world in society now one thing that we
already know from the history is that
all kibbutzim
thought that that was a very bad idea at
some point and alki would see him in the
late 70s and
early 80s they cancel basically the
they bring kids to back home but more
than this
in the reality of the of the life in
kibbutzim even in the
period where children lived communally
was that women
ended up working more in the traditional
stereotypical
female occupation like they were the
nanny in the
children residents was always a woman
and women
ended up working more in the services
and less in the productive
branches and also many people say that
actually the voice of women in the
general assembly was less
important so it was mostly the men that
were doing the talking
and women were not taken very seriously
into economy this is one reason that i
when i told you
that the economist would tell the
kibbutzim to create the kibbutz
just very similar to the way they did
but not exactly
that's one of the reasons is because if
for sure it would give more voice to
women and so it was it
created this contradiction between the
equality that they strive for and the
reality of women working in
and doing their traditional works yeah
and
frankly that doesn't surprise me i mean
to be honest we were emerging from 10
000 years of patriarchy at that time to
expect the switch to be thrown
would have probably been unrealistic you
know obviously the world's come a long
way since then
but we're still not all the way there so
like anything it's a process of
maturation
and understanding and change you touched
on this which is the bringing the
children back to the family
and one of the things i don't freaking i
don't remember was your book or henry
near's book but i do recall that
some of the earliest kibbutz's were
kind of radically and ideologically
anti-bourgeois
family and some of them even advocated
free love
and not even having couples in housing
etc
and certainly all the children being
raised together from very young ages was
part of that
but over time quite the opposite
occurred you know
if anything kabut's people may be more
bourgeois in their family structures
than average in israel
and as you point out the return of at
least the younger children there was i
understand it
older children still live communally and
like 12 or over
something like that in in many kibbutz
so part of the early ideology at least
for some was radical anti-bourgeois
family but that didn't really work out
so well
right so the the i think that even a
deeper reason for the
children's residence was the idea that
they wanted to educate their children
to the you know to the kibbutz ideals
into the kibbutz
communal way of living and they thought
that one way of doing it was
to have them all equal and give them
equal opportunities and to
talk to them about equality for you know
from a very early age and the literature
on the communal residences of children
is
is large and somewhat complicated it's
not a very simple story of it was great
or it was terrible it's a little bit
like a summer camp in the us you know
how some children love it
and they think it was terrific and they
got to hang out with all their friends
and they didn't have to
worry about their parents all the time
and other the more sensitive children
find it uh
terrible and they want to go go home and
so it's a little bit a mixed
experience it was a mixed experience
like that at some point it was mostly
the parents that just wanted their
children
they just kind of felt that it was just
not natural for them
to have their children not grow in their
houses
that led to a push to to to abolish them
i would say i would touch another thing
that you said that is a bit more broader
than the children residences the
bourgeois idea that you mentioned
so at some level the most
puzzling period of kibbutzim the most
interesting one if you want is exactly
those middle years
in the 60s and 70s when they were no
longer based on agriculture only
they had industry there was more
heterogeneity people worked in all sorts
of different occupations
they had factories at some level it's
not very surprising maybe that
a small group of people who come
in a young age to a country full of
uncertainty
you know from socialist backgrounds
create them for themselves a
community that is based on equality it
is most surprising that
by the second generation and third
generation people who grow up
into it didn't decide intentionally to
join
and now many people working in many
different occupations
that are rather heterogeneous relative
to their parents
they still choose to live in an equal
sharing society and create one that is
rather successful but that was exactly
when in the eyes of
israelis some of the contradictions of
the kibbutz started to emerge ah so you
are
talking about equality and simple life
but all i can see
is that you have a nice swimming pools
and
uh and beautiful uh paths and so you're
more bourgeois
than even the rest of us there was also
there were some contradictions you know
around the time when people started to
come to israel from more middle eastern
countries
faraday jews the prime minister at the
time
ben gurion asked kibbutzim if they can
host some of these
people as a first house in the you know
let them work and
adjust to the new country and what you
hear a little bit when you hear
this ferrari jews talk about their
experience you hear many people say
things like
we were very welcome in their fields but
not very much in their dining halls
again creating a sense that in the eyes
of some people they were more like a
club elitist club
then they were an inclusive society
for everybody to be fair for them it's a
very it's a very
tricky business and the socialist and
zionist ideology
often clashed with one another so if you
know on the one hand
as zionists they wanted to when jewish
people come they want to host them but
on the other hand
as socialists they cannot be they are
not allowed to exploit outside
labor and so i think that he would seem
have a number of contradictions
built in them at some level some of the
a lot of their beauty
is that they are flexible enough to
adjust the rules to the practicality of
life
in order to survive rather than like
many other communes in history just to
collapse as soon as
there are some practical difficulties
yeah and i think that
that's actually a very good takeaway
that even the ones that were very
ideological
were not insane about it i suppose the
ones that were insane probably just went
away but you know they
they were pragmatic they were empirical
they responded to reality
let's move on to our next section here a
lot of what we've been talking about is
the
pre-crisis period and you know as you
said the
the high water mark probably of the
kibbutz movement was in the
60s and 70s and then came the 1977
election of the likud party historically
all the coalitions that had governed
israel had had as a very significant
component the labor party or its
antecedents and those parties had always
been pretty strongly aligned with one or
more of the kibbutz movements and had
in various ways helped subsidize the
kavitz movement provided favoritism for
boots nicks to enter the government and
the military etc
but with the election of the lacude that
started to change and then the debt
crisis of the 80s maybe talk a little
bit about that
yeah so the kibbutzim were successful
in the 60s and 70s and they had high
quality of life
in part because they were able to
successfully
solve the incentive problems and they
were able to
create successful factories and they
they got it right at some level
but we can't forget that entirety's
economic success was because of
governmental support
so uh the kibbutzim have always enjoyed
the support of the government and before
the state of
israel was established the jewish
agencies
in the form of land in the form of
subsidies for water
in the form of tax advantages
and so on there was somehow an explicit
and implicit
understanding between them and the
jewish
agencies that if things go wrong they
have
access to credit from the government now
over time especially starting the 80s a
number of uh
factors started to make it would seem
less attractive one of them
is the one you talk about declining
governmental support
with the rise of the right-wing
government for the first time in
israel's history in 1977
that government no longer viewed
kibbutzi
as so special they viewed them more as
the creation of the labour party
that came before them and there was that
definitely was one
reason that made he would seem less
attractive other things were
a decline in idealism in the second and
third generation so again
the idea that when living in a kibbutz
is not your
choice but you default you are born into
it the second and third generation were
no longer as idealistic
as the founders of kibbutzim there was
the declining governmental support and
then but there was also the
a high-tech boom in israel you know
israel
in the 90s have this high-tech boom
that make it more attractive for kibbutz
members
especially one that can earn more
outside that gives them an increased
incentive to
to live if you want israel itself was a
relatively
egalitarian country before the in this
before the 80s and it becomes less
egalitarian
and so all these reasons made hebrew
seem less attractive and then of course
there was the financial crisis
the financial crisis was it's probably
too complicated to talk about it for too
long here i talked about it a lot in the
book
but there were a number of reasons for
the financial crisis one of them israel
in the time was in a period of high
inflation
israel in the 80s was in a period of
very high inflation 400 percent yearly
inflation
and the kibbutz uh as you know always
had a as i told you always had this
credit in the government they took large
loans they took loans to in part to
bring the children from the children
residences back home they needed to
expand the housing stock
so they took loans they took loans to
expand their industries
and loans were not linked to inflation
so it was very it's very easy to repay a
loan when it's
not linked to inflation and the
inflation is 400
but then at some point the government
decided to take action
and they had a stabilization program and
as part of it they
left interest rates very high and made
the loans that the kibbutzim were taking
very expensive
and uh very difficult for kibbutzim to
repay
and then kibbutzim at some level were
too big to fail
and so they had like a number of
agreements with the government and the
banks and the kibbu team
that basically uh restructured the loans
uh
postponed some of their loan payments
and erased some other parts of the loans
it's uh
and essentially though required he would
seem to reduce their living standards
by by quite by quite a bit so that's
that's about the crisis i can't i can i
can stop here i can talk more about that
the reforms that came later
yeah i think that's a good place to stop
for a second and then what happened was
quite interesting
and probably predictable i'd love to get
your thought on that which is
you know beginning with these crises
there was much more of a movement away
from
pure radical egalitarianism but at least
by my read it was on a continuum
some stayed all pure egalitarian or damn
close to it
others ended up almost pure capitalist
and then a bunch were in between
and strikes me what a wonderful found
experiment for an economist right
here you go from radical egalitarianism
to a
spectrum of moves away from it or
staying with it and
as you have done you collected a lot of
data and we're able to
you know find out what the different
alternatives to radical egalitarian
led to with respect to some of your
predictions so you know maybe talk about
that just a little bit maybe how you
gathered the data and then talk about
some of the findings
yes so jim so this is exactly what i
thought when i was doing my phd at
northwestern and so that's what i
decided
to write my dissertation about
i noticed that kibbutzim they had very
different experience with the financial
crisis some were hit a lot some were hit
a little bit
and then later they had very different
experience with the with the shift
away from equal sharing
and so after they just to give some
context after the
a few years after the financial crisis
starting the mid 1990s
kibbutzim started a process that is
called privatization i put
privatization in quotation mark because
privatization in kibbutzi means
doesn't mean completely privatize
everything it really means just a series
of reforms
starting first with just reforms that
were meant to avoid waste
and increase productivity things like
you have to pay for your food and
electricity so that you don't leave your
air condition on
all day and don't fill up your plate
with
too much food and things like taking
some of the kibbutz branches
and bring some outside managers that
actually know how to manage rather than
kibbutz members
that maybe don't have that much
experience with management so this was
like the first
early waves of the of reforms but then
later they started with really deeper
reforms
of differential wages so shifting from
the very idea
of the full equal sharing shifting away
from equal sharing to various degrees as
you said
some kibbutzim shifted to a large degree
away from equal sharing
others to just a small degree and others
about 20 percent of kibbutzim
remain completely egalitarian and so i
decided to start by
writing about that you know at some po
at some level if i if i go back in
in my the way my thinking evolved on the
kibbutz at some level the idea of how we
create an equal society
and all those questions i was at first
interested in
were a little bit too big for me to get
started with and so i started with
smaller question
collecting data you know reading the
sociology the history the economics of
kibbutzim talking to kibbutz members of
all ages
to reading a lot of the history but also
collecting
data on all the 120 000 members in the
260 he would see him over the last many
many years
and one of the first questions i started
with is asking the questions of which he
would seem
decide eventually to stay equal in which
he puts him decide to shift
away from equal sharing and the main
thing that i find
is that once the financial crisis hit
and this was as you said
at some level it's a great experiment to
to understand what are some of the
limits of equality
and one of the things that i find in the
data
is that after the financial crisis and
once kibbutzim
were required to reduce the living
standards quite a bit
a massive process of brain drain started
so i take the data i take two censuses
of population
before and after the financial crisis
and i find that the
and i link them and i find that people
that were more educated and skilled
were much more likely to leave kibutim
and about 20 25 percentage of
of skilled people leave kibbutzim
and then what i find more interesting
than that i find that
kibbutzim that remained rich after the
financial crisis so some kibbutzim were
not hit
very much by the financial crisis they
remained richer they did not were not
required to reduce the living standards
by a lot
they are the ones that tend to remain
equal so keep
rich hibu team maintain the high degree
of equality
he would seem that were hit by the
financial crisis and we required to
reduce the living standards
are the first to shift away from equal
sharing
and once they do fewer and fewer of the
talent of the educated members
exit and so that was like my main
finding that
richard kibbutziem maintain a higher
degree of equality and again
in my mind this raised the question of
to what extent the some of the social
democratic countries like against norway
and sweden
that of course are different than
kibbutzim they are based on a
free market but they have more higher
degree of equality
to what extent they are able to maintain
such a generous welfare state
because they are so rich you know like
what have what would happen if they
if there was an oil crisis in norway and
norway would become less rich
would there be more break if the kibbutz
is any guidance
uh perhaps there would be more brain
drain and they would have to most to
struggle more with the welfare state
that's a very interesting insight and
probably a very important insight for
anyone who wants to build
a community which probably is the degree
you want to be able to maintain
equal sharing egalitarianism you better
figure out how to be
really successful in the world right
because it's hard to maintain that
in poverty right a question i have for
you i i don't recall if you looked into
this or not
i think you did which is did ideology
did have a measurable impact for
instance in the kibbutz artsy folks
move less far from equal sharing or not
yes ideology did overall so
he boots members from the rt movement
the one that
is more ideological we're slower to
shift away from equal sharing they were
less likely
to shift away from equal sharing kibbutz
members
in kibbutzim where the voting was more
to the left if you want
in national governments were less likely
to shift so there is some evidence that
ideology play a role in fact you know
like the twenty percent of kibbutzim
that maintain equal sharing are now
they call themselves the communal stream
and they are
rewriting if you want the id not
rewriting but actually they say that the
other kibbutzim are rewriting
the original ideology and that and they
restate their commitment to
ideas of of equality so ideology did
play a role but i have to say that
i concluded that if ideology maybe had
a bigger role in the creation of
kibbutzim to some degree
in their long success but economic
factors were more important
in explaining the shift away from equal
sharing than ideological factors
okay that's interesting a couple things
that you talked about for sure
were you analyzed in the book we hit it
about earlier which is the increase in
financial return to education
changed a fair amount about how
education particularly higher education
was consumed but also how seriously
people took education
at the secondary level yeah so maybe
that's a maybe that's one place where i
can explain a little bit in more detail
some of the data work that we do if it's
interesting
for your readers let's do it so again
this is work always with victor lavier
who is one of the world experts in
economics of education
and basically what we do is we collected
data imagine you want to know what
happens when key boots shift away from
equal sharing
so you know that economic theory says
that
people let's say invest one of the
reasons why people invest in
in education and why they study hard and
why they choose certain fields is
because of the expected financial
returns
but usually this is very difficult to
test in the data
because it's very difficult to test
because we very rarely see
strong changes in the rates of returns
to education yes we have some
indications that as
the returns to education increase over
the last 20 or 30 years in the us
whether or not people study more but
it's very hard to observe
sharp changes in the returns to
education so he would see many of them
shifted away from equal sharing and some
of them didn't
and they shifted in different time and
so what we can do is we collected data
on all the high school students in
kibbutzim data from the ministry of
education and from the labor bureau of
statistics where we can see
actually how seriously did kibbutz
members study
before the reform and after the reform
in kibbutzim that reformed late
in kibbutzim early and then we can
actually look at whether the cohorts of
students
of kibbutzim that reformed earlier start
to take more seriously once the kibbutz
reform and that's
basically one the first thing we find is
that yes
once the ki boots reform high school
students start to have to get better
grades
they are more likely to get a
matriculation certificate and more
likely to continue
into higher education and then we ask
the question what happens
to people who were young adults at the
time the dirty boots reform
and that's where we find that they start
to shift away from humanities again and
towards sciences
and that was suggestive that maybe the
returns to education
aren't everything but it's certainly the
case that once the returns to education
increase
kibbutz members still boot students
start to take school more seriously and
kibbutz members become more likely
to acquire education in fields that
offer higher financial
returns makes sense another one i found
very interesting is that you studied the
impact of
inequality with respect to the number of
children families chose to have
yeah that's a very interesting one
that's actually not one of my studies i
described this study in my book but it's
a study by abby ebenstein and
and moshe hasan and a number of authors
in the from the hebrew university
where they look at what happens once the
kibbutz shift away from equal sharing to
the number of children
and the idea again is if you think about
it in
a in a fully egalitarian kibbutz it is
cheaper to raise your own children yes
so imagine that you you
whether you have two children or four
children or six children uh if you get
an equal share anyway
then it's less expensive to raise
children and so they test
this idea and find that uh
once key would seem shift away from
equal sharing you start to see a decline
in the
and families have to pay for their for
raising their own children
they start to see fewer number of
children interesting
another study again i don't remember was
yours or somebody else's was you were
able to do
a or someone was able to do a measure of
work ethic
and how that varied with inequality yes
so so the work ethic is that that's that
gets us to the more
suggestive world rather than conclusive
world because but it's based on that
on some surveys of public opinion in
kibbutzim you see some suggestive
evidence although here we don't have the
clean design that i was describing to
you earlier about
comparing kibbutzim data from earlier
and later and things like this this is
just suggestive evidence that shows
that on the one hand the self-reported
work ethics
seems to be higher in kibbutzim that's
reformed
then in kibusi they didn't reform
suggesting that maybe work ethics
improved although at the same time if
you when you ask people about
how they feel about the social life and
the social atmosphere in the kibbutz
you see that the more egalitarian
kibbutzim actually have a higher
reported degree of happiness from their
social life and so again
indicating that it's a trade-off you
know between incentives and
you know like an inequality yeah you got
my next one i was going to ask you about
which was the happiness rating and so
it's a trade-off between work ethic and
happiness
right yeah why is that not surprising
right yeah
and of course the the magnitude of some
of the efficiencies that were squeezed
out by these reforms were quite
substantial i think i recall reading
that
in some kibbutz the electricity use went
down 40
when people had to start paying for it
right and there were you know
significant savings in food
when for instance you know people either
had to pay for the food or they
outsourced
the dining hall to companies that
optimized in running dining halls things
of that sort
yeah but at the same time i remember you
know when i started to visit my
my uncles and aunts later after the he
was reformed in the beginning
i remember that there was a sense in
which the neighbors that
befall were so important and and it was
very important social aspect of life
and there was some disillusion at first
of like oh you know before i appreciated
you because you
actually earned the same as me even
though you you you were the secretary of
the kibbutz but now you earn more for it
so why should i appreciate it
but i so there was some period in which
especially the
the older generation the one that didn't
really love the idea of the reform
felt that there is a sacrifice in terms
of
uh in terms of happiness and in terms of
the social atmosphere but i do think
that there is a revival in kibbutzim now
and both kibbutzim that were formed in
kibbutzim that didn't reform
they now have good social life and they
are all happy and even kibbutzim that
did reform by the way they are still
based on mutual aid and mutual
assistance and
and the equality and helping others is
still a building block
and it's still important to them even if
they shifted away from equal sharing so
i think
the kibbutzim did get to a sweet spot
whether or not they reformed
and and and they are an example of how
if you're flexible enough
to respond to the changing world around
you you can actually make a quality
work for you that's good
getting a little short on time i would
kind of like to have jumped into where
things are today but
let's instead go to how your insights
provide some information about other
attempts at communal living around the
world and through history
yes so again if you are me you risk
seeing
you risk seeing kibbutzim everywhere so
while they are only in israel and only a
small percentage i think that i see
elements of kibbutzim
in many places so we talked a little bit
about the
social countries that the social
democratic countries i see elements of
kibbutzim i see elements of kibbutzim in
developing countries in village
economies
i see them in even in organic in
partnerships that are based on more
revenue sharing
i see them in the in the arguments about
between democrats and republicans about
high taxes versus low taxes if you want
the egalitarian ki boot is a hundred
percent tax rate i see them everywhere
but i think that
if we are short on time maybe i will say
that uh the the general lessons from the
kibbutz are maybe even broader than
than each of the examples the way the
way i see them if i circle back to that
question of like
could we create an egalitarian society
and
and what we learn from kibbutzim about
it i think that my
my lesson is that yes full equality is
possible
but it has a price it is possible
because kibbu teams survived for
more than a hundred years and they are
one of the most important social
experiments in equal sharing and they
survived for a long time and they were
successful
it is possible because even today in the
21st century there are
30 or 40 kibbutzim that are still based
on full equal sharing
and it is possible because even reformed
kibbutzim are still taking care of the
weak and the old members and they are
based on from their safety net
and and otherwise on their mutual aid
and assistance
but but i think that but it has a price
in the sense that kibbutzim a small
community full equality has a price
because he would seem a small community
and when you try to implement equality
and socialism
at the country level you very quickly
get like a soviet union or something
with heavy restrictions on individual
freedom and
otherwise it has a price because of what
we talked about that
lack of privacy and common property that
was so important to deal with incentive
problems
are also sacrifices that many of many
people are not willing to make and that
explains why they are
so rare and again it is has a price
because of the
the screening in entering to the kibbutz
means that the equality inside the
kibbutz does come at the price of
excluding many others from the
quality arrangement that's all useful
insights you also
look with some care at some examples in
the united states which despite its
you know capitalist roots has also
always been a hotbed of utopian style
communes right
you looked at some non-religious ones
most of which failed as i understand and
then you look in some detail at the
hutterites which is
very successful but rather extreme
example maybe you could talk a little
bit about both the non-religious
utopian ones and ones like the
hutterites
yes so i have a chapter in the book
about the stability of communes and i
find many
many of the inherent problems associated
with equal sharing of resources that is
very similar in kibutim and other
community it did mean that most communes
in history
have been short-lived and communes that
were better able to structure themselves
to solve this problem
lasted longer and were more successful
religious communes for example ended up
being more successful than
than secular ones often times there is
interesting work by ovid and by
and by by sources about about these
religious communes
and others i find that one
characteristics of short-lived communes
is that members did not share
ideological training and had very
different backgrounds
and many communes that collapsed early
were forming a haste or with little
ideological preparation
and so on so the brotherhood of
cooperative and the new harmony and
others
other communes that were more long-lived
had more shared ideology
they were able to adjust their structure
as lives around them changed like the
hutterites and the
ammanna and the shakers and others
and one of the interesting things that i
find there is that as the society around
so if you think if you focus on
successful communes for example
you look at what happens when society
around them changes and you know
typically the way it works is there is
modernization in society out around you
the returns to skill in the outside
world increases
and it becomes more difficult to sustain
your commune what do you do
and so if you want the successful
communist took one of two
ways one is the kibbutz way the kibbutz
way is you become more like society
around you so you're like oh my okay
it's becoming more difficult to sustain
full equality because people want to
live then why don't we become somewhat
less egalitarian
and we offer members more options like
society around us
there is also another way that
successful communities
have taken which is to become more
inward looking if you want so
rather to become even to stick more to
your original principles maybe to not
allow
your members to see what their outside
option and how the outside world is like
this is maybe more a little bit more
like the hatterite example
yeah of course the hutterites are
physically quite remote and they even
speak their own language right sort of a
dialect of german as i understand it
yes and that makes it more difficult for
me for people to
evaluate how successful they might be in
the outside world for example if they
decide to leave
yeah though i will say those kinds of
things strikes me as more cult-like than
healthy societies where you
try to isolate people make it really
difficult to exit etc
yeah but many of them but many of them
have but you know to be fair and you
know this is a
you should really in my book when in
others they have been
adapting themselves to the changes in
the modern world and they have
been doing it in such a way that many of
their members and even the young ones
are happy about and so
they are doing their best to adopt as
well
okay sort of a last topic here before we
wrap up
you know between radical capitalism on
one side and
equal sharing on the other there's lots
of other settings you know one i
stumbled across in my reading of various
books on the kibbutz movement was a
movement in israel called moshav i think
it is where individual family units
operate their farms with their
businesses but they cooperate in
marketing and buying
the amish and mennonites do that to some
degree
in the united states we have things like
co-ops employee-owned co-ops
and we have companies that have large
amounts of profit sharing etc
what are some of the broader lessons
from your work about thinking about
how to increase egalitarianism in
society in general
without necessarily going all the way to
small
subdunbar number units we can talk about
the examples that that you gave
the moshav and the cooperatives but i
think that if in the last couple you
know i think i would focus even on the
on the bigger picture on like society in
general and i think that
what one of the things that the broader
lessons that i learned uh
and and the way i want to relate it to
to lessons to other societies
is that in a world where
there is such an increase such a rising
income inequality and in the united
states today you know the top
one percent owns i don't know like 30
percent of the
of the of the wealth it is very natural
that people start to ask themselves the
question
of whether and how we can create more
equal
sharing societies then at some level the
kibbutz the way i viewed it in my book
and in my research is that it is an
experiment
of a social experiment that went exactly
the other way so it went
to the full equality way and
nevertheless was able to be successful
subject to sacrificing in privacy
and in some other way but if the key
boots as a full equal sharing was able
to be
successful but probably not in a way
that most people would like to live in
but there are egalitarian societies and
countries like again
i'm always thinking norway and sweden
and the nordic model
that were able to successfully take some
of what
many of us instinctively feel is good
about equality
and about having making sure that people
have sufficient living and they
there is no poverty there is a generous
welfare state you don't let people
die of hunger and the people in general
feel that they are happy and having
fulfilled life
with the market forces because you know
norway is a market economy and
it's not like a centrally planned
economy and so somehow
i'm hoping that my research helps us not
just a bit more
towards thinking about how we can enjoy
the
benefits of equality while thinking
about the incentives and the free market
and you know i
the nordic model is one place that is
doing it very well
all righty ron thank you very much this
has been an incredibly interesting
conversation
and again i would point listeners who
want to learn more to ron
bromitski abramitsky i'll get that right
and his very interesting book i mean i
was utterly fascinated with this book i
was about halfway through and i started
googling saying i gotta track this
author now god damn it
the mystery of the kibbutz egalitarian
principles in a capitalist world
thanks for being here team thank you so
much for having me it was fun
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music dot com